Guide to the H.F. Broch De Rothermann Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
H. F. Broch de Rothermann papers
1916-2001
1953-1986
YCGL MSS 2
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4
(11 boxes)
The H. F. Broch de Rothermann Papers are composed primarily of correspondence which documents the life and career of the Austrian writer Hermann Broch, the father of Hermann Friedrich Broch de Rothermann. The collection spans the years 1916 to circa 2001, with the bulk of the material falling between 1953 and 1986. Major topics include republication of Hermann Broch's writings, Broch scholarship, and other aspects of the reception history of Broch's works. Also present are materials relating to Broch de Rothermann's work in the United States Office of Strategic Services (OSS) during World War II, writings and drawings by Broch de Rothermann, and other papers relating to him. Papers relating to the OSS include reports on the development and effectiveness of propaganda, American support for resistance in areas occupied by Germany, American occupation of Italy and Germany, and interrogation of German soldiers and other prisoners by the American army; samples of military and civilian propaganda in German, Italian, French, Russian, and other languages; correspondence and documents about Broch de Rothermann's service, discharge, and return to the United States after the war; and a photograph of unidentified soldiers, possibly including Broch de Rothermann. Propaganda samples include drawings made by artist Saul Steinberg.
Broch de Rothermann, H. F.
Steinberg, Saul, 1914-1999
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were collected by Broch de Rothermann in his capacity as literary executor for his father's works and primarily deal with aspects of Broch's life and works after his death in 1951. The papers were donated to the Beinecke Library in installments by H. F. Broch de Rothermann between 1970 and 1990.
Materials in the Addition Series were gifts of H. F. Broch de Rothermann, 1990-1994; gift of Sachiko Yoshizawa Broch de Rothermann, 1997; gift of Bradford McCormick, 1997, and transferred from Yale University Manuscripts and Archives, 1992. Material transferred from Yale University Manuscripts and Archives was purchased from Sachiko Yoshizawa Broch de Rothermann by Michael Keller in 1991. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 10 (audiocassette and videocassettes): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Associated Materials
For additional archival materials concerning Hermann Broch, see the Hermann Broch Archive (YCGL MSS 1) at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
H. F. BROCH DE ROTHERMANN (1910-1994)
Hermann Friedrich Broch de Rothermann was born in Vienna on October 4, 1910, the only child of Hermann Broch and Franziska von Rothermann Broch. He attended schools in Vienna, Switzerland, Great Britain, and France and received diplomas from Haute École des Sciences Politiques et Financières in Paris and the Academy of Commerce in Vienna. During the 1930s he travelled, served as secretary of the International Literary Agency, and worked as a correspondent for the Neue Freie Presse of Vienna. He was a patient in Sanatorium Löw in Vienna recovering from a skiing accident at the time of Anschluss. In June 1938 he was adopted by his uncle Rudolf von Rothermann in Hungary.
Broch de Rothermann left Austria in March 1939, lived in French internment camps from September 1939 to June 1940, spent a year in the French Foreign Legion, and emigrated to the United States in September 1941. Shortly thereafter he married Eva Wassermann, but was divorced in 1949. In 1942 he became head of the Short Wave Listening Post for the New York Daily News and from 1943-46 served in the United States Office of Strategic Services (OSS) in Italy and Austria, leaving that service with the rank of lieutenant colonel. After 1947 he held a number of conference interpreter positions for the United Nations and on a free-lance basis. He married Sachiko Yoshizawa in 1961.
During his later life, Broch de Rothermann published translations, devoted a great deal of his time to discussing Hermann Broch with scholars, advised the Library and the curator of the Yale Collection of German Literature, and was a generous donor to the Broch Archive. Broch de Rothermann died in 1994.
Scope and Contents
The H. F. Broch de Rothermann Papers are composed primarily of correspondence which documents the life and career of the Austrian writer Hermann Broch, the father of Hermann Friedrich Broch de Rothermann. The collection spans the years 1916 to circa 2001, with the bulk of the material falling between 1953 and 1986. Major topics include republication of Hermann Broch's writings, Broch scholarship, and other aspects of the reception history of Broch's works. Also present are materials relating to Broch de Rothermann's work in the United States Office of Strategic Services (OSS) during World War II, writings and drawings by Broch de Rothermann, and other papers relating to him.
Series I, Correspondence, (Boxes 1-8) consists of correspondence between Broch de Rothermann and editors, publishers, scholars, and friends of Hermann Broch, including correspondence with Dániel and Daisy Bródy, Pantheon Books, Rhein-Verlag, and Suhrkamp Verlag. The letters of prominent Broch scholars, such as Manfred Durzak and Paul Michael Lützeler, shed light on the author's current importance as a literary figure. Also present are the letters of Broch de Rothermann's grandparents, uncle, mother, and stepmother (Annemarie Meier-Graefe Broch), as well as those of friends, including Hannah Arendt, Marion Canby, Erich and Alice Loewy Kahler, Edith Levy, Edith Ludovyk-Gyömröi, Robert Pick, Jean Starr Untermeyer, and Hermann J. Weigand.
Series II, Addition (Boxes 9-11), is divided into three subseries. Correspondence, circa 1970s-circa 2001, consists mainly of letters between Broch de Rothermann and correspondents also represented in Series I, including Annemarie Meier-Graefe Broch, Franziska von Rothermann Broch (accompanied by photographs and identification documents), other Broch family members, Alice Loewy Kahler, Edith Ludovyk-Gyömröi, Paul Michael Lützeler, and Suhrkamp Verlag. Also present are some additional correspondents and unidentified letters.
United States Office of Strategic Services, circa 1944-circa 1946, consists of papers relating to Broch de Rothermann's work in the OSS Morale Operations Branch during World War II. Papers include reports on the development and effectiveness of propaganda, American support for resistance in areas occupied by Germany, American occupation of Italy and Germany, and interrogation of German soldiers and other prisoners by the American army; samples of military and civilian propaganda in German, Italian, French, Russian, and other languages; correspondence and documents about Broch de Rothermann's service, discharge, and return to the United States after the war; and a photograph of unidentified soldiers, possibly including Broch de Rothermann. Propaganda samples include drawings made by artist Saul Steinberg.
Other Papers, most undated, include drafts of a short story, a screenplay, and other writings by Broch de Rothermann; drawings by Broch de Rothermann and Gregor von Rezzori; and videocassette and audiocassette interviews with Broch de Rothermann.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Correspondence, 1916-1990. II. Addition, circa 1944-circa 2001.
Austrian literature; Authors and publishers -- Austria; Authors and publishers -- Germany; Authors, Austrian -- 20th Century -- Archives; Critics -- Austria; Critics -- Germany; Critics -- United States; Publishers and publishing -- Austria; Publishers and publishing -- Germany; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American; World War, 1939-1945 -- Propaganda; World War, 1939-1945 -- Prisoners and prisons; World War, 1939-1945 -- Underground literature; Audiocassettes; Audiovisual materials; Videocassettes; Arendt, Hannah, 1906-1975; Broch, Franziska von Rothermann; Broch, Hermann, 1886-1951; Broch, Johanna Schnabel; Broch, Josef; Broch de Rothermann, H. F.; Broch family; Bródy, Daisy; Brody, Daniel, 1883-1969; Canby, Marion G. (Marion Gause), 1885-1974; Durzak, Manfred, 1938-; Kahler, Alice Loewy; Kahler, Erich, 1885-1970; Krafft-Kennedy, Ludwig; Levy, Edith Jonas; Ludovyk-Gyömröi, Edith; Lützeler, Paul Michael, 1943-; Meier-Graefe, Annemarie, 1905-1994; Pick, Robert, 1898-; Schlant, Ernestine; Steinberg, Saul, 1914-1999; Untermeyer, Jean Starr, 1886-1970; Wellwarth, George E., 1932-; Weigand, Hermann J. (Hermann John), 1892-1985; Yamaguchi, Kōichi; Pantheon Books; Rhein Verlag; Suhrkamp Verlag; United States. Office of Strategic Services; United States. War Department. Strategic Services Unit
- Correspondence, 1916-90; Series I; 3.5; (8 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged alphabetically by surname of correspondent. General correspondence with editors, publishers, friends, and scholars, relating to Hermann Broch and unidentified correspondence is placed at the end.
  - Akademie der Diözese Rottenburg- Stuttgart, 1985-86 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alpern, Ariane, 1981-82 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Arendt, Hannah, 1955, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bergland Verlag, 1965-66 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bernheim, Kurt, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bernheim, Mark, 1981-85 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Boehlich, Walter
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Suhrkamp Verlag, Box 6 folder 116
  - Broch, Annemarie Meier-Graefe, 1950-71 (Box 1, Folder 7-19)
  - Broch, Annemarie Meier-Graefe, 1972-85 (Box 2, Folder 20-22)
  - Broch, Franziska von Rothermann, 1969-74 (Box 2, Folder 23-32)
  - Broch, Friedrich Josef ("Fritz"), 1938 Aug 28 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Broch, Josef and Johanna Schnabel, 1916-39 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Bródy, Dániel and Daisy, 1966-69 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    See also: Rhein-Verlag, Box 5 folder 100
  - Brude-Firnau, Gisela, 1965-79, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Buchhändler-Vereinigung GMBH, 1967-70 (Box 2, Folder 37-39)
  - Buchhändler-Vereinigung GMBH, 1971-73 (Box 3, Folder 40-41)
  - Bunzel, Joseph H., 1952-69 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Canby, Marion Ponsonby Gause ("Lady"), 1951-61, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 43-44)
  - Claassen Verlag, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Commentary, 1957, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Conroy, Kathryn
    See: Pantheon Books, Box 5 folder 89
  - Dahl, Sverre, 1974-85 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Deutsche Buch-Gemeinschaft, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Deutsches Literaturarchiv, 1974-86 (Box 3, Folder 49-50)
  - Doctorow, Erica, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Dokumentationsstelle für neuere österreichische Literatur, 1966-81 (Box 3, Folder 52-53)
  - Donald, Roger
    See: Little, Brown and Company, Box 4 folder 81
  - Durzak, Manfred, 1965-74 (Box 3, Folder 54-58)
  - Ebner, Jeannie
    See: Literatur und Kritik, Box 4 folder 80
  - Faber du Faur, Curt von, 1957 Dec 19 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Farrar, Straus & Giroux, Inc., 1985-86, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 60-61)
  - Feldman, Theo, 1951 Jun 30 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Fischer, Heinrich R. ("Harry"), 1971 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Greenberg, Martin
    See: Commentary, Box 3 folder 46
  - Hack, Berthold
    See: Buchhändler-Vereinigung GMBH, Box 2 folder 37
  - Hassold, Ernest C., 1962-63 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Herzog, Anja, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Irinoda, Masaaki, 1981-85 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Jonas, Klaus W., 1963-80 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Kahler, Erich and Alice Loewy ("Lili"), 1952-53 (Box 3, Folder 68-69)
  - Kahler, Erich and Alice Loewy ("Lili"), 1953-86 (Box 4, Folder 70-72)
  - Kessler, Michael
    See: Akademie der Diözese, Box 1 folder 1 Rottenburg-Stuttgart
  - Kiss, Endre, 1977-90, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Krafft-Kennedy, Ludwig, 1951-64 (Box 4, Folder 74-78)
  - Levy, Edith Jonas, 1973-86 (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Linnekuhle, Mr.
    See: Deutsche Buch-Gemeinschaft, Box 3 folder 48
  - Literatur und Kritik, 1970-71 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Little, Brown and Company, 1970-75, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 81-82)
  - Ludovyk-Gyömröi, Edith, 1971-77 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Lützeler, Paul Michael, 1969-77 (Box 4, Folder 84-88)
  - Lützeler, Paul Michael, 1978-88 (Box 5, Folder 89-92)
  - Meyer, Jochen
    See: Deutsches Literaturarchiv, Box 3 folder 49
  - Pantheon Books
    - Correspondence, 1962-75 (Box 5, Folder 93-94)
    - Royalty statements, 1964-72 (Box 5, Folder 95)
  - Pick, Robert, 1945-57 (Box 5, Folder 96)
  - Pötzl, Hermine, 1968-71 (Box 5, Folder 97)
  - Politzer, Heinz, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 98)
  - Réalités, 1967-71 (Box 5, Folder 99)
  - Rhein-Verlag, 1952-67 (Box 5, Folder 100-08)
  - Riemer, Willy, 1974-86 (Box 6, Folder 109)
  - Ritzerfeld, Helene
  - Roditi, Edouard, 1984-86 (Box 6, Folder 110)
  - Rothstein, Irma, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 111)
  - Saiko, Magdalena, 1970-71 (Box 6, Folder 112)
  - Schlant, Ernestine, 1967-82 (Box 6, Folder 113)
  - Seitz, Bruno, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 114)
  - Steinberg, Michael P., 1981-86 (Box 6, Folder 115)
  - Steinecke, Hartmut, 1967-68 (Box 6, Folder 116)
  - Straus, Roger W.
    See: Farrar, Straus & Giroux, Inc., Box 3 folder 60
  - Suchy, Viktor
    See: Dokumentationsstelle für neuere österreichische Literatur, Box 3 folder 52
  - Suhrkamp Verlag
    - Correspondence, 1966-77 (Box 6, Folder 117-28)
    - Correspondence, 1978-87 (Box 7, Folder 129-32)
    - Royalty statements, 1971-82 (Box 7, Folder 133-38)
  - Sulzer, Dieter
  - Torberg, Friedrich, 1959-81 (Box 7, Folder 139)
  - Unseld, Siegfried
  - Untermeyer, Jean Starr, 1955-75 (Box 7, Folder 140-41)
  - Weigand, Hermann John, 1954, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 142)
  - Weil, G.
    See: Réalités, Box 5 folder 99
  - Wellwarth, George E., 1968-73 (Box 7, Folder 143)
  - Wienold, Götz, 1965-66 (Box 7, Folder 144)
  - Winkel, Maria Angela, 1970, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 145)
  - Wolff, Helen, 1980 Mar 3 (Box 7, Folder 146)
  - Wysling, Hans, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 147)
  - Yamaguchi, Koichi, 1981-86 (Box 7, Folder 148)
  - Correspondence with editors, publishers, friends, and scholars, relating to Hermann Broch, 1953-88 (Box 8, Folder 149-61)
  - Unidentified, 1954-55 (Box 8, Folder 162)
- Addition, circa 1944-circa 2001; Series II; 1.5
  Arrangement
  This series is divided into three subseries: Correspondence, United States Office of Strategic Services, and Other Papers. Within each series, materials are arranged alphabetically by name or subject.
  - Correspondence
    - Bernheim, Mark (Box 9)
    - Broch, Annemarie Meier-Graefe (Box 9)
    - Broch, Franziska von Rothermann (Box 9)
    - Broch, Friedrich Josef and Alice (Box 9)
    - Kahler, Alice Loewy (Box 9)
    - Kerschbaumer, Marie Thérèse (Box 9)
    - Kiss, Endre (Box 9)
    - Ludovyk-Gyömröi, Edith (Box 9)
    - Lützeler, Paul Michael (Box 9)
    - McCormick, Bradford (Box 9)
    - Meyer, Jochen (Box 9)
    - Skwara, Erich Wolfgang (Box 9)
    - Steinberg, Michael P. (Box 9)
    - Suhrkamp Verlag (Box 9)
    - Yamaguchi, Koichi (Box 9)
    - Unidentified (Box 9)
  - United States Office of Strategic Services
    - "Samples of Austrian Propaganda" (Box 9)
    - Other propaganda samples and notes (Box 9)
    - "Inter-Office Correspondence, Personal Status Documents" (Box 9)
    - "Inter-Office Memos, Worksheets, Assignments" (Box 9)
    - "SI Reports" (Box 9)
    - Other reports, correspondence, and documents (Box 9)
    - Other original envelopes (Box 9)
  - Other Papers
    - Drawings by H. F. Broch de Rothermann and Gregor von Rezzori
      See: Oversize, Box 11
    - Interview with H. F. Broch de Rothermann, 1987-1988; 1; 00:30:31 (Box 10, Item barcode 39002091243106)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Interview with H. F. Broch de Rothermann, 1 hour 45 minutes, 1997-11-08; YCGLMSS2_0001; 1; 02:16:43 (Box 10, Item barcode 39002102370229)
    - Interview with H. F. Broch de Rothermann, 140 minutes, assembled but not edited, 1997-02-24; YCGLMSS2_0002; 1; 02:22:42 (Box 10, Item barcode 39002102370237)
    - Obituary. clipping, photocopy (Box 10)
    - Writings (Box 10)
- Oversize, 0.08; (1 box)
  Oversize (Box 11) is composed of materials from Series II.
  - Drawings (Box 11)